Guide to the Cyril Frank Elwell Papers M0049
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Cyril Frank Elwell Papers
1930-1961
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Elwell, C. F. (Cyril Frank)
M0049
3 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Scope and Contents Note:
These papers contain several versions of Elwell's autobiography, including one written under a pseudonym and correspondence with possible ghost writers, especially R. B. Stone. Also included are engineering papers, clippings, biographical materials, and correspondence.
Biographical Note:
Cyril Frank Elwell (1884 – 1963) was an American inventor and pioneer in the development of radio-telegraphy and long-distance communication. Born in Melbourne, Australia in 1884 to an American father and a German mother, Elwell arrived in the United States in 1902. He studied electrical engineering at Stanford University, graduating with an engineering degree in 1907. While he first was involved with electric metallurgy, in 1908 he began research in wireless communication after investigating a system for voice transmission invented by Francis Joseph McCarty (1888-1906) six years earlier. Elwell founded the Poulsen Wireless Telephone and Telegraph Company, later renamed Federal Telegraph Company in 1909. By 1910 Elwell had sucessfully demonstrated voice communication between Stockton and Sacramento, California. Equipment and technique rapidly improved and by 1911 Federal Telegraph was prepared to bid on contracts to provide Navy communication to Hawaii. After a dispute with the Federal Telegraph board of directors, Elwell resigned in 1913 but continued his research, joining the short-lived Universal Wireless Syndicate. During World War I he was a consulting radio engineer for the French and Italian governments. Subsequently he moved to England where in the early 1920s he established and managed the company C. F. Elwell, Ltd., originally to mainly supply wireless apparatus for maritime communication but later manufacturing home radio receivers for the emerging radio broadcasting service. While in England he also became involved in other electronics enterprises, including collaborating with Lee de Forest on talking pictures with the British de Forest Phonofilms Company. He also briefly worked on motion picture sound in France. Elwell was a founding investor in the Mullard Radio Valve Company, manufacturers of vacuum tubes. After his term as director at Mullard, he returned to the United States in 1947 and was a consulting engineer for Hewlett Packard. He died in 1963.
Provenance:
Gift of Mrs. Cyril Frank Elwell, 1963
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.None.
Related Materials
Stanford holds a few related collections:
MSS PRINTS 0085 "600-foot tower design for Federal Telegraph Co.: blueprints and typescript, 1912" https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/5175668
MISC 1035 "Clippings about Elwell and his work, 1912-1934" https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4703395
Radio -- History; Electrical engineering; Elwell, C. F. (Cyril Frank)
- Autobiography
  - Autobiography. Notebook with typed copy and manuscript corrections. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Autobiography. Notebook with typed copy but no corrections. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Autobiography. Notebook with typed copy of marked pages 2-66. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Autobiography. Notebook with typed copy and manuscript corrections. Version C. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Autobiography. Typed copy of tape recorded reminiscences, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Autobiography. Typed copy of tape recorded reminiscences, revised. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Autobiography. Version P begining with page 2. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Autobiography. Another version. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Revised autobiography with the aid of R. B. Stone. Outline for possible publisher. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Revised autobiography written under the name Frank Rossa. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Autobiography. Notes for Stone. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Autobiography. Miscellaneous notes. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Autobiography. Notes for Stone. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Autobiography. Notes for Stone. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Autobiography. Van Etten, deForest and Hewlett Packard material. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Autobiography. Miscellaneous notes. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Correspondence
  - Letters, outgoing, 1941 Jan. 16 -1961 Feb. 28. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Letters, incoming, A - Z. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Letters not to Elwell but concerning his work. (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Clippings
  - Clippings, 1930s. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, 1940s. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, 1950s. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Articles, speeches, papers, etc.
  - Speeches and articles by Elwell. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Magazine articles pertaining to Elwell. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Contracts and certificates. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Financial papers. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Engineering papers. Notebook of designs and circuits. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Engineering papers. History of Radio, notes by Elwell. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Engineering papers. Structural designs. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Engineering papers. Antennas (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Engineering papers. Antennas (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Engineering papers. Transisters (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Engineering papers. Lapp radio material. (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Engineering papers. Radio towers. (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Engineering papers. Linear electron accelerator. (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Photographs
  Scope and Contents
  Approximately 150 early 20th century photographic prints of radio towers, equipment and people. There are also portraits of Elwell.
  - "The C.F. Elwell Collection of Photographs & Equipment Used in Connection With the First Continuous Wave Commercial Stations on the West Coast Built by Federal Telegraph Company" (Box 5, Folder 1)
    listing for exhibit with most of the photos listed
  - Portraits of Elwell, residences, other people (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photo album pages (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Anderson" (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - South San Francisco/California (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - El Paso, Texas (Box 5, Folder 7)
    One photo from the El Paso file is in Folder 1 (portrait of C.V. Logwood)
  - England (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Primarily Newcastle & Horsea Island
  - Ireland (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Lyon/France (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Rome, Italy (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Misc. Europe (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Romania, Hungary, Malta
  - Egypt (Box 5, Folder 13)